Guide to the Charles and Joy Sheffey Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Charles and Joy Sheffey Papers
1913-1985
1922-1943
RG 219
Yale University Divinity School Library
10
(17 boxes)
Charles and Joy Sheffey were American Methodist medical missionaries who served in Wembo Nyama, Belgian Congo (now Democratic Republic of the Congo) between 1922 and 1944. Letters, journals, and writings of Charles and Joy Sheffey document their medical work and record their reactions to the culture and environment they encountered in Africa.
Sheffey, Charles
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Grace Sheffey Webb, 2009
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
1894 June 19 Charles Phillips Mahood Sheffey born in Lynchburg, VA, son of Edward Fleming Sheffey and Mattie Mahood Sheffey
1907 May 26 Mae Joy Burch (Sheffey) born in Danville, VA, daughter of Nannie Towsey Burch and Rev. William G. Burch, a Methodist minister in the Virginia Conference
1911-1915 CPMS attended Randolph Macon College, receiving A.B. and M.A. degrees
1921 CPMS graduated from School of Medicine of Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, followed by additional training at New York Postgraduate Medical School; he also served as an intern at Norfolk Protestant Hospital
1922-1926 CPMS served as medical missionary in Wembo Nyama, Belgian Congo (now Democratic Republic of the Congo) under the Methodist Board of Missions
1920s JBS attended Longwood College and Lynchburg College, continuing her nursing training in Richmond, VA and Philadelphia, PA
1930 CPMS and JBS married while CPMS was on extended stay in U.S. due to illness of his father
1931 CPMS and JBS sailed for Africa, spending some months at École de Medécine Tropicale in Belgium en route; arrived in Congo in July
1931-1944 CPMS and JBS ran a medical training center in Wembo Nyama and provided surgical services to a region that spanned a 500-mile radius.
1931 Daughter Grace born; she later attended the Central School for missionary children in Lubondai
1935 Daughter Nancy born
1945 Sheffey family returned to Lynchburg, VA where CPMS practiced medicine until his retirement in1969
1957 CPMS received honorary LL.D. degree from Randolph Macon College
1985 March 8 CPMS died
Scope and Contents
Letters, journals, and writings of Charles and Joy Sheffey document their medical work and record their reactions to the culture and environment they encountered in Africa. Circular letters and writings provide substantive documentation of their life and work in the Belgian Congo between 1922 and 1944. Letters to and from their children Grace and Nancy provide detail about the life of missionary children in Africa. Of particular note are the records that Charles Sheffey kept to describe operations performed at the Wembo Nyama hospital and surrounding area. Collected material includes documentation of the Methodist Mission, school books in African languages used in its schools. Photographs document the Sheffey family and their mission in Wembo Nyama
The collection contains a notable number of diverse artifacts. These include African musical instruments, a "witch doctor's magic gourd", jewelry, metal implements, and textiles.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Notes and Diaries
IV. Biographical Documentation
V. Collected Material
VI. Photographs
VII. Artifacts
Missions -- Congo (Democratic Republic); Methodist Episcopal Church -- Missions -- Africa
- Correspondence, 1914-1983; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Charles to Joy, prior to their marriage, 1930 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Charles to/from Joy, primarily prior to their marriage, 1930, 1937, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Charles and Joy from their parents, primarily prior to their marriage, 1922-1931 Jan (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Charles and Joy from their parents, 1931 Feb - Dec (Box 1, Folder 4, 5)
    - Charles and Joy to/from family members including excerpts of letters from Joy describing native customs, lions, locust., 1932 -1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Charles and Joy to/from family members, including excerpts of letters from Joy describing locusts, incident with leopard, medical work and her letter describing the Mission's historical pageant (1939), 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charles and Joy to their daughter Grace, written from Wembo Nyama while Grace was away at Central School in Lubondai, 1941 Aug- 1943 Nov (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
      Scope and Contents
      Letters contain descriptions of everyday life at the Mission
    - Nancy Sheffey to her sister Grace, written from Wembo Nyama while Grace was at Central School in Lubonda, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Interesting child's perspective on life at the Mission
    - Grace Sheffey Webb to/from her aunt Grace, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence
    - Published and mimeographed letters by Charles Sheffey describing his work in Africa, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Primarily typescript letters from CPMS to churches describing his work, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - To/from others, including letter from President Franklin Roosevelt thanking JBS for Belgian Congo stamps, and circular letters of JBS, 1935-1940 Mar (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - To/from others, including circular letters of JBS describing their work, 1940 Nov - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - To/from others, including re. book re. Sheffey family history, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Letters of others, including excerpts from letters of Paul Alexander from Belgian Congo (1961), 1914-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings, 1924-1960, n.d.; Series II
  - By Charles Sheffey
    - Poems #4-91, 1925-1927, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
    - Articles and essays, including "Surgery by Lamplight in the Congo", "Early Work among the Lepers of the Belgian Congo", "Death and Funeral Rites Among a Primitive People", "Two Hundred Miles Across Africa on a Bicycle", "African Youth and a Christian World", reports on medical work, 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - By Joy Burch Sheffey
    - Essays, stories, newsletters, including series of "Tom Tom Notes", "Twenty-five Years of History Pass in Review", "Black Reflects Lights", others, 1933-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Essays and stories, including "Ekanda, One of God's Black Children", "Great African Chief Reaches Journey's End", "On to Africa; a brief study of the Belgian Congo... for use in Sunday Schools and Public Schools", 1939, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Essays and stories, including "What the Native African Eats", "Again to the Heart of Africa", "African Womanhood", "A Leopard in a Rabbit Trap?", "Spreading the Gospel Among the Bush-people", "Congo Doctor", 1943,1944, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - By Grace Burch Sheffey
    - Compositions, including "My Favorite Vacation Spot", "Sandcastles", "Irish Superstitions", etc., 1946, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - By others
    - Including poem "The Missionary Call" by Joy's mother Nannie Towsey Burch, essays by Lilian Mahood, "My Trip Home: Belgian Congo - USA 1946" by Serena Kelly, 1939, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Notes and Diaries, 1922-1942; Series III
  - Three notebooks with handwritten notes by CPMS recording operations he performed, 1931-1944 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Miscellaneous notes by CPMS and JBS, 1931-1932, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Line a Day" diary of CPMS, 1923-1925 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "My Travels" notebook and small diary, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Bound journal of CPMS, 1922-1925 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Biographical Documentation, 1913-1985; Series IV
  - Biographical sketches of CPMS and JBS, 1931-1985 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Student Volunteer Movement applications (Charles Phillips Mahood Sheffey), 1921 (Box 3, Folder 34A)
  - "Wedding Memories" volume, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Newspaper clippings about CPMS, 1917-1974 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - Health information and miscellaneous biographical documentation about families, 1915-1972 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Information about grandfather of CPMS, Rev. Robert Sayers Sheffey, including book Brother Sheffey a Christian Who Knew the Power of Prayer by Willard Sanders Barbery, 1922-1946, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39, 40)
  - Information about father of CPMS, Edward F. Sheffey, 1918-1933, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous family biographical information, 1913-1969,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Genealogical documentation re. Sheffey and Mahood families (Box 4, Folder 43-46)
- Collected Material, Series V
  - Related to Methodist mission in Congo medical work, 1937, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Related to Methodist mission in Congo conference, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Handmade Bible story booklet in African language (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Related to Central School for Missionaries' children, Lubondai, 1939, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Issues of "Jungle Log" published by the students of Central School for Missionaries' Children, Lubondai, 1942-1946. (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - African language writings, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Maps of Congo; book Belgian Congo at War (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Miscellaneous programs, cards, clippings (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - African language school books, Bible lessons, catechism, primarily published by the Methodist Episcopal Church Mission, Wembo Nyama, 1940-1944, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 55-60)
  - Pamphlets from "Little Books for Africa" series, published in London: "The Leopard and the Goat", "Tombo Temba" "Hausa Tales", "The Blood Brother", 1927, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Books from the library of CPMS and JBS: Africa Disturbed; Along the African Path; Appointment Congo; The Call of the Congo; Congo Crosses: A Study of Congo Womanhood; The Cross Over Africa; Daughter of Africa; Doctor of the Happy Landings; God's Ravens; More About Africa; Out of Africa (by Emory Ross) (Box 6)
  - Books from the library of CPMS and JBS: Rural Prospect; The Salt Baby; Seeing Africa; Sons of Africa; Tales from Africa; Walter Russell Lambuth; The Way in Africa (Box 7)
- Photographs, Series VI
  - CPMS, JBS and daughters (See also Box Ov1 for framed portraits of CPMS), 1920s-1940s, n.d (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Members of extended Sheffey family, 1923, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Wembo Nyama mission and en route, 1930s, 1940s (Box 5, Folder 64-65)
- Artifacts, Series VII
  - Textiles: ten woven mats (Box Ov1)
  - Textiles: book bags, placemats, napkin, trivets (Box Ov2)
  - Textiles: woven mats (Box Ov3)
  - Metal: 12 inch knife, 1 copper hatchet, Y-shaped hairpin; letter opener; copper cross; metal anklet (Box Ov4)
  - 3 hand made cloth dolls, 3 strands of red and white beads; 1 strand of witch doctor's beads with leopard tooth; headband for mourning; native comb; fan; ceremonial rattle; baby rattle (Box Ov5)
  - Wooden stool; feathered witch doctor's hat (Box Ov6)
  - Underwood typewriter (Box Ov7)
  - Woven carrier, grass skirt, tortoise shell; "witch doctor's magic gourd"; thumb piano (Box Ov8)
  - Large woven basket; Musical instrument made from snakeskin and ivory (Box Ov9)
  - Wooden messenger drum with drum sticks and metal staff (Box Ov10)